Guide to the Archie Boston papers, 1963-2018 and undated RL.11673
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Archie Boston papers
1963-2018 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Boston, Archie, 1943-
John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
RL.11673
8.0 Linear Feet
African-American graphic artist, professor and advertising executive based primarily in California; principal in the firm Archie Boston Graphic Design. Collection includes print materials, posters, sketches, greeting cards, correspondence, as well as audiovisual materials in multiple formats (DVDs, tape reels, and film reels) that document Boston's career in advertising and graphic design as well as his academic life at California State University-Long Beach. Companies represented include California Plum, Raisin and Apple Advisory Boards, FMC, Motorola, Pentel, Raytheon and Yamaha. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
Arrangement
Organized into the following series: General Files; Creative Work; and Audiovisual Materials.
Biographical / Historical
African-American graphic artist, professor and advertising executive based primarily in California; principal in the firm Archie Boston Graphic Design. Born 1943, in Clewiston, Florida and grew up in St. Petersburg, Florida. After graduating from Chouinard Art Institute in Los Angeles with a BFA in Advertising Design, Boston and his brother Brad Boston, formed their own ad and design agency Boston & Boston Design in 1967. In 1969, Boston started working for the ad agency Botsford Ketchum. During his eight years with Botsford Ketchum, Boston worked with clients such as Pentel, Motorola, and Yamaha. Simultaneously he started Archie Boston Graphic Design, an advertising and design agency. In 1977, Boston received his Master's Degree in Liberal Arts from the University of Southern California and was hired as a lecturer in the Department of Art at California State University Long Beach (CSULB) where he was a member of the Design department which included the Visual Communication Design Program. He chaired the graphic design program for 12 of his 32 years before retiring in 2009. He was the first African-American elected president of the Los Angeles Art Directors Club, where he served two terms. Boston published two memoirs -- Fly in the Buttermilk: Memoirs of an African American in Advertising Design & Design Education (2001) and Lil' Colored Rascals in the Sunshine City (2009). He has also produced two historical documentaries, 20 Outstanding Los Angeles Designers and The Black Pioneers of the Sunshine City.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. However, original audiovisual materials are closed until use copies can be produced.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Archie Boston Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2018.
Related Materials
Related materials may be found in the following Hartman Center collections: J. Walter Thompson Company. Denis Lanigan Papers; McCann-Erickson Audiovisual Collection; The Duplex Advertising Company. Billboard Images and Records
Collection Overview
Collection includes print materials, posters, sketches, greeting cards, correspondence, as well as audiovisual materials in multiple formats (DVDs, tape reels, and film reels) that document Boston's career in advertising and graphic design as well as his academic life at California State University-Long Beach. Companies represented include California Plum, Raisin and Apple Advisory Boards, FMC, Motorola, Pentel, Raytheon and Yamaha. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
Advertising; Advertising -- Design; Advertising agencies -- United States -- History; Graphic design; Graphic artists -- United States; Advertising executives -- United States; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; Archie Boston Graphic Design
- General Files, 1963-2018 and undated; 1
  General
  This series includes Boston's two memoirs, university work both as a student and professor, exhibition catalogues and materials, ad designs, preparatory materials for his documentary, as well as published mentions from newsletters, magazines, and newspapers.
  - ADLA (Art Directors Club of Los Angeles) activities, 1973-1976 and undated (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes photographs, memoranda, posters, newsletters, and press mentions all pertaining to Archie Boston's activity in the ADLA
  - Awards, 1973-2007 and undated; 2 folders (Box 1)
    AIGA (American Institute of Graphic Art) awards as well as other advertising awards.
  - Awards, 1973-2007 and undated (Box 7)
    AIGA awards as well as other advertising awards. Also includes an award from the California State Assembly recognizing Archie Boston's Outstanding Professor of the Year Award (2004).
  - Correspondence, 1974-1991; 2 folders (Box 1)
    Correspondence includes Archie Boston's transition from the Botsford & Ketchum ad agency to academia and thank you letters from various individuals throughout Archie Boston's career.
  - Documentary materials, 2016-2018 (Box 1)
    Press clippings, interviews, scripts, drafts, and shooting schedule all pertaining to the documentary Black Pioneers of the Sunshine City. Digital copy of the documentary is located in the AV files, RL11673-OP-004.
  - Exhibition materials--My Soul Is a Witness, 2014 (Box 1)
    Table of contents for DVD series, see RL11673-OP-025.
  - Exhibition materials--Other exhibitions, 1991-2017 (Box 1)
    Correspondence and catalogs for "Visual Perception"; "Back to the Future"; and "Designs of Dissent" exhibits
  - Exhibition materials--Watts Riot Festival, 1976 (Box 1)
    Includes correspondence between Boston and the California Museum of Science and Industry on Boston's exhibit on the Watts Riot Festival. Also includes photos from Boston's MA Thesis that were to be part of this exhibit. The remainder of these photos can be found in Box 6.
  - Exhibition materials, 1976-2013; 2 folders (Box 6)
    Photos of the Watts Riot Festival that were part of Boston's MA Thesis and that were set to feature in an exhibition at the California Museum of Science and Industry (exhibition was canceled). The remainder of these photos can be found in Box 1 in "Exhibition Materials."
  - Print materials--Fly in the Buttermilk, 2001 (Box 2)
  - Print materials--Lil' Colored Rascals in the Sunshine City, 2009 (Box 2)
  - Published mentions, 1963-2017; 3 folders (Box 2)
    Mentions of Archie Boston's design work and/or competitions he has judged. From 1963 to the early 1970s.
  - Published mentions, 1963-2017; 5 folders (Box 3)
    Mentions of Archie Boston's design work and/or competitions he has judged. From 1971 to 1978.
  - Published mentions, 1963-2017; 3 folders (Box 4)
    Mentions of Archie Boston's design work and/or competitions he has judged. From 1980 to 2017.
  - Published mentions, 1972-2018 (Box 9)
    Newspaper and newsletter clippings.
  - University materials, 1982-2004 and undated; 4 folders (Box 4)
    Contains correspondence, M.A. thesis, and Outstanding Professor Award materials from California State University-Long Beach as well as miscellaneous university designs and publications.
  - University materials, 1994-2005 and undated; 5 folders (Box 5)
    Includes Outstanding Professor Award materials, Wang Family Excellence Award application, and post-tenure review files all from California State University-Long Beach.
  - University materials, 1980-1987 and undated (Box 7)
    Includes miscellaneous designs, posters, and newsletters from California State University-Long Beach.
  - University materials, 1983 and undated (Box 9)
    Includes miscellaneous posters related to California State University Long Beach.
- Creative Work, 1965-2017 and undated; 2
  This series consists primarily of ad designs and other graphic designs Archie Boston created. Includes self-promotional ads from his agency Boston & Boston and ads for clients he created while employed at Botsford Ketchum. Also includes designs he created on his own later in life (posters, social activist materials, and greeting cards).
  - Botsford & Ketchum, approximately 1969-1977; 1
    - Accounts, approximately 1969-1977 (Box 1)
      clients include Braemar, Yamaha, and the California Plum, Raisin and Apple Advisory Board
    - Accounts, approximately 1969-1977 (Box 4)
      Clients include Braemar, Yamaha, and the California Plum, Raisin and Apple Advisory Board
    - Industrial accounts, approximately 1969-1977 (Box 7)
      Includes ads for Motorola, FMC Corporation, Varian, Braemar, Yamaha, Raytheon, Galaxy Homes
    - Industrial accounts, approximately 1969-1977 (Box 9)
      Includes ads for Motorola, FMC Corporation, Varian, the California Plum, Raisin, and Apple Advisory Board, among other companies.
    - Lloyd Bank, approximately 1969-1977 (Box 7)
      Advertisements for Lloyds Bank designed during Boston's employment at Botsford & Ketchum. Television advertisements for Lloyds Bank can be found in AV 3 RL. 11673
    - Pentel, approximately 1969-1977 (Box 1)
      Includes the ad "I told them what to do with their pens." Assortment of undated Pentel ads but the date range covers the period of time Archie Boston worked at Botsford & Ketchum
    - Pentel, approximately 1969-1977 (Box 7)
    - Pentel, approximately 1969-1977 (Box 9)
  - Botsford & Boston, approximately 1969-1977; 2
    - Self-promotional, 1970s (Box 9)
      Includes the "For Sale" ad and the "Uncle Tom" ad.
  - Archie Boston Graphic Design, 1986-2017 and undated; 3
    - Designs and advertisements, 1976-2017 (Box 1)
      Includes logo designs and posters for social causes and other designs.
    - Designs and advertisements, 1986 and undated (Box 7)
      Designs for Centinela Hospital and self-promotional ads.
    - Designs and advertisements, undated (Box 8)
      self-promotional ads and public service ads
    - Designs and advertisements, 2014 and undated (Box 9)
    - "If Black Lives Matter" poster series, undated (Box 1)
      Prints of digital images on RL11673-OP-001
  - Other Work, 1965 and undated; 4
    Includes Archie Boston's student work, his ad designs for the ADLA, as well as holiday and greeting cards.
    - ADLA ads, undated (Box 8)
      Ads designed for ADLA including the Santa Claus ad and the "Call for Entries" ad.
    - Holiday cards, undated (Box 1)
      Archie-Boston designed holiday cards and stationery. Other designs and cards can be found in Box 8.
    - Holiday cards, undated (Box 8)
      Archie Boston-designed greeting and holiday cards. Other designs can be found in Box 1, "Holiday cards."
    - Student portfolio, 1965 (Box 7)
      Ad sketch designs from when Boston was a Master's student.
    - Student portfolio, 1965 (Box 8)
- Audiovisual Materials, 1986-2016 and undated; 3
  This series includes Boston's final university lecture, television commercials for his client Lloyds Bank from when he was employed at Bostford Ketchum, two documentaries (20 Outstanding LA Designers and Black Pioneers of the Sunshine City), a retrospective film exhbition, and digitial images of his "If Black Lives Matter" posters.
  - If Black Lives Matter--10 posters, undated (Box AV1, Optical-disc RL11673-OP-001)
    Hard copy of posters can be found in Box 1
  - Archie Boston's Final University Lecture, 59:00, 2010 (Box AV1, Optical-disc RL11673-OP-002)
  - Boston's Students' Work, 2000-2005 (Box AV1, Optical-disc RL11673-OP-003)
  - Black Pioneers of the Sunshine City, 48:00, 2016 (Box AV1, Optical-disc RL11673-OP-004)
    Documentary written and produced by Archie Boston on the history of segregation in his native St. Petersburg, Florida. Notes and preparatory materials for the documentary can be found in Box 1.
  - Black Pioneers of the Sunshine City, 48:00, 2016 (Box AV1, Optical-disc RL11673-OP-005)
  - Archie Boston 1943-, undated (Box AV1, Optical-disc RL11673-OP-006)
  - 20 Outstanding Los Angeles Designers--Q&A, 37:00, 1986 (Box AV1, Optical-disc RL11673-OP-007)
    A set of interviews Archie Boston conducted with designers in LA in 1986, includes a Q&A. Spans from RL11673-OP-007 to RL11673-OP-024.
  - 20 Outstanding Los Angeles Designers--April Greiman, 35:00, 1986 (Box AV1, Optical-disc RL11673-OP-008)
  - 20 Outstanding LA Designers--Huerta Design, 33:00, 1986 (Box AV1, Optical-disc RL11673-OP-009)
  - 20 Outstanding Los Angeles Designers--Dennis Juett, 37:00, 1986 (Box AV1, Optical-disc RL11673-OP-010)
  - 20 Outstanding Los Angeles Designers--John Follis, 21:00, 1986 (Box AV1, Optical-disc RL11673-OP-011)
  - 20 Outstanding Los Angeles Designers--Louis Danziger, 25:00, 1986 (Box AV1, Optical-disc RL11673-OP-012)
  - 20 Outstanding Los Angeles Designers--Ray Engle, 20:00, 1986 (Box AV1, Optical-disc RL11673-OP-013)
  - 20 Outstanding Los Angeles Designers--Keith Bright, 16:00, 1986 (Box AV1, Optical-disc RL11673-OP-014)
  - 20 Outstanding Los Angeles Designers--John Cleveland, 37:00, 1986 (Box AV1, Optical-disc RL11673-OP-015)
  - 20 Outstanding Los Angeles Designers--James Cross, 20:00, 1986 (Box AV1, Optical-disc RL11673-OP-016)
  - 20 Outstanding Los Angeles Designers--Saul Bass, 58:00, 1986 (Box AV1, Optical-disc RL11673-OP-017)
  - 20 Outstanding Los Angeles Designers--Ken Parkhurst, 36:00, 1986 (Box AV1, Optical-disc RL11673-OP-018)
  - 20 Outstanding Los Angeles Designers--Marvin Rubin, 29:00, 1986 (Box AV1, Optical-disc RL11673-OP-019)
  - 20 Outstanding Los Angeles Designers--Robert Miles Runyan, 22:00, 1986 (Box AV1, Optical-disc RL11673-OP-020)
  - 20 Outstanding Los Angeles Designers--Marian Sampler, 33:00, 1986 (Box AV1, Optical-disc RL11673-OP-021)
  - 20 Outstanding Los Angeles Designers--Ken White, 27:00, 1986 (Box AV1, Optical-disc RL11673-OP-022)
  - 20 Outstanding Los Angeles Designers--Don Weller, 18:00, 1986 (Box AV1, Optical-disc RL11673-OP-023)
  - 20 Outstanding Los Angeles Designers--Doug Boyd, 33:00, 1986 (Box AV1, Optical-disc RL11673-OP-024)
  - My Soul is a Witness--Advice to Students, 2:00, 2014 (Box AV1, Optical-disc RL11673-OP-025)
    Part of a retrospective exhibition. The list of chapters in this DVD collection can be found in "Exhibitions" in Box 1.
  - My Soul is a Witness--What Did I Say?, 2:47, 2014 (Box AV1, Optical-disc RL11673-OP-026)
  - My Soul is a Witness--Yesterday and Today, 3:03, 2011 (Box AV1, Optical-disc RL11673-OP-026A)
  - My Soul is a Witness--1976 Watts Summer Festival Activities, 4:50, 2014 (Box AV1, Optical-disc RL11673-OP-027)
  - My Soul is a Witness--20 Outstanding LA Designers, Q&A, 37:00, 2014 (Box AV1, Optical-disc RL11673-OP-028)
  - My Soul is a Witness--Fly in the Buttermilk, 4:00, 2014 (Box AV1, Optical-disc RL11673-OP-029)
  - My Soul is a Witness--Lil' Colored Rascals in the Sunshine City, 4:20, 2009 (Box AV 2, Optical-disc RL11673-OP-030)
  - My Soul is a Witness--Overcoming the Odds, 5:17, 2014 (Box AV 2, Optical-disc RL11673-OP-031)
  - My Soul is a Witness--Walk Around Heaven, 3:47, 2014 (Box AV 2, Optical-disc RL11673-OP-032)
  - My Soul is a Witness--You are My Friend, 4:27, 2014 (Box AV 2, Optical-disc RL11673-OP-033)
  - My Soul is a Witness--The Red Clay of Alabama, 4:45, 2014 (Box AV 2, Optical-disc RL11673-OP-034)
  - My Soul is a Witness--Oh Lord, Let it Be, 3:36, 2014 (Box AV 2, Optical-disc RL11673-OP-035)
  - My Soul is a Witness--To God Be the Glory, 4:48, 2014 (Box AV 2, Optical-disc RL11673-OP-036)
  - My Soul is a Witness--Santa Fe, New Mexico, 3:41, 2014 (Box AV 2, Optical-disc RL11673-OP-037)
  - My Soul is a Witness--Someone Made You For Me, 2:37, 2011 (Box AV 2, Optical-disc RL11673-OP-038)
  - My Soul is a Witness--Holiday Greetings Slide Show, 2:55, 2014 (Box AV 2, Optical-disc RL11673-OP-039)
  - KFI--Archie Boston Profile, undated (Box AV 3, Audio-reel RL11673-RR-001)
  - Television Commercials for Lloyds Bank, undated (Box AV 3, Film-reel RL11673-F16-001)
  - Juniors and Seniors Majors' Work, approximately 2004 (zip drive) (Box AV 3)